I have to be honest with you unless I'm
growing muscle at steroid rates there is
zero chance I would consider doing
regular ice baths but when you have
athletes popular Health enthusiasts and
others who seem to be pretty bullish on
dunking themselves in very cold water
for health benefits it's worth a
scientific glance now there might be
other health benefits like increases in
brown fat that I'll discuss in other
content but for now I'd like to discuss
the impact it has on muscle growth
because there's a recent analysis that
pulled together all of the studies on
cold water immersion and detailed the
effects it has on muscle hypertrophy or
muscle growth the analysis was limited
to randomized control trials that
included at least two lifting sessions
per week and lasted a minimum of four
weeks in duration including only healthy
participants now let's look at the data
on the left side we have resistance
training alone on the right side we have
resistance training paired with cold
water immersion the studies are listed
on the left like the usual Forest plot
for those following physionic for some
time will know and the results of each
study are represented by the things that
look like Hills if you squint maybe
we'll zoom in here and you can see that
there's a black dot Dot and a black line
under the hill those represent what's
known as a median value it's the result
of that particular study and is less
prone to skewing heavily in One
Direction there's so much more to that
sentence that needs to be unpacked but
uh since you're not here for a
statistics lesson I'll refer you to my
course on a study analysis Linked In the
description for more
information in very basic terms see the
dotted line going up if the studies move
to the right of that there's a muscle
growth effect and you can focus on the
hill at the very bottom which is the
average of all the included studies
overall the results indicate there's a
muscle growth effect of resistance
training now don't act so shocked yes I
know I'm revolutionizing your concept of
reality with that information but that's
what the data says lifting weights makes
you gain muscle just accept it but we're
not here to learn about lifting weights
resistance training we're here about
cold water immersion so applying the
same rules that we outlined we can focus
our attention on the bottom again and we
see that it too seems to lean to the
right indicating there might be an
effect in fact the researchers mentioned
the effect is and I quote small to
negligible yet while the effect might be
at best small that would still indicate
there's a positive effect right well not
quite because the data that we just went
over is simply seeing if there's an
effect indicating if resistance training
plus cold water immersion leads to
muscle growth the answer seems to be yes
but what we're really interested in is
if it leads to more muscle growth than
resistance training alone in fact the
title of this video would be pretty
misleading if cold water immersion
provided a benefit to muscle growth and
we wouldn't want to clickbait anyone on
the internet right
right anyway for that information the
researchers compared both data sets that
we just went over against each other
instead of independently we see that
here note the dotted line and note the
two conditions on either side overall
comparing against each other it is more
better beneficial not to include cold
water immersion as muscle gains are
likely greater with resistance training
alone as with anything in science what
you compare against makes all the
difference in our interpretation but all
that said why would cold water immersion
blunt our muscle growth capabilities
actually there are situations where cold
water immersion improves outcomes which
might speak to why certain athletes
should still consider using it but there
are some nuances to get into I'll
discuss those in the extended version of
this video included with the physionic
Insiders which is linked in the
description if you are so interested it
includes all my work my videos my
articles podcasts summaries private
Community guides and templates and more
like I said in the description well
there are several mechanisms that are
outlined from Vaso constriction of the
blood vessels meaning uh clamping down
of the blood vessels supplying blood to
the muscles to reduced activity of the
muscle growth enzymes in fact both of
those could influence each other uh
reduce blood flow means less oxygen and
nutrient delivery to the tissue so it's
muscle that critically needs it both to
recover and grow the lack of nutrients
to the muscle cells downregulates and
even inhibits muscle growth Master
enzymes like mtor which control muscle
protein synth is the general production
of muscle proteins necessary for growth
Beyond those two mechanisms it's also
believed that uh cold exposure reduces
the activation of uh immune cells and
during muscle growth immune cells can
play an important role in clearing up uh
damage components of the muscle but more
specifically secreting different
molecules to encourage muscle
healing that's just a few of the
proposed mechanisms and that's not all
encompassing so the take away here is
don't do it or at least uh if your goal
is maximal muscle growth don't do it if
it's uh masochism by all means knock
yourself out but be sure to scream loud
enough as you get in so that I can hear
you as I bundle up all cozily reading
more studies on things that actually
work like the studies that I cover in
this video right here thanks for
watching
[Music]